IAM vs. Northwest Airlines and Miscellaneous others Arbitration Proceedings 5298
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
IAM vs. Northwest Airlines and Miscellaneous others Arbitration Proceedings
1940-1949
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5298
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence, transcripts.
Records consist of documentation of labor-management dispute settlement and wage stabilization cases brought before various mediation panels of the National and Region 2 War Labor Boards, as well as the Non-Ferrous Metals Commission of the U.S. National War Labor Board.
2293704
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 25, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The National War Labor Board, a tripartite body established in 1942 by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, was charged with acting as an arbitration tribunal in labor-management dispute cases, thereby preventing work stoppages which might hinder the war effort. It was also responsible for determining wage adjustments in accordance with anti-inflationary wage stabilization criteria and policies.
The Board was initially divided into 12 Regional Administrative Boards which handled both labor dispute settlement and wage stabilization functions for specific geographic regions. The National Board further decentralized in 1943, when it established special tripartite commissions and panels to deal with particular industries on a national basis.
Scope and Contents
This collection reflects the Board's decision-making and internal communication processes, and documents Board policy on no-strike pledges, grievance and arbitration procedures, union security, management rights, maintenance of membership, anti-inflationary wage control policy, and fringe benefits.
The bulk of the collection consists of materials pertaining to labor dispute settlement cases. Includes awards, decisions, and reports and recommendations of mediation panels; hearings transcripts, and documents used as evidence in hearings; and statements, briefs and answers of employers and unions. Documents generated by the War Labor Board also include memoranda, press releases, bulletins and reports concerning directives for case handling, administrative procedures and regulations, and summaries of Board actions and decisions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Wage-price policy -- United States; War and emergency powers -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects -- United States; Arbitrators, Industrial.; Absenteeism -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Agricultural machine industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Airlines -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Aircraft industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Brewing industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Coal mining industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Container industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Copper mining -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Cosmetics industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Electric industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Food industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Fur trade -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Glass manufacture -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Iron industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Machine industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Meat industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Metal-workers -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Mining industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Musicians -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Nonferrous metal industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Paint industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Petroleum industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Plumbing and heating industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Potash industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Public utilities -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Retail trade -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Shipbuilding industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Steel industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Stevedores -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Telecommunication -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Textile industry -- New England; Arbitration, Industrial -- Textile industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Zinc mining -- United States; Bargaining unit -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Checkoff -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Coal mining industry -- United States -- Military aspects; Collective bargaining -- Musicians -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Radio broadcasting -- United States; Collective labor agreements -- Stevedores -- United States; Collective labor agreements -- Telecommunication -- United States; Contracting out -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Defense contracts -- United States; Employee fringe benefits -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employee fringe benefits -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employee fringe benefits -- Telecommunication -- United States; Employees, Dismissal of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Transfer of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Grievance procedures -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Grievance procedures -- Telecommunication -- United States; Hours of labor -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Hours of labor -- Steel industry -- United States; Hours of labor -- Stevedores -- United States; Insurance -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Life insurance -- Law and legislation -- United States; Job descriptions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Job security -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Job security -- Fur trade -- United States; Labor disputes -- Musicians -- United States; Labor disputes -- Steel industry -- United States; Labor disputes -- Stevedores -- United States; Labor productivity -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Layoffs -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Management rights -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Merchant marine -- United States -- Military aspects; Mine safety -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Musicians -- Salaries, etc. -- United States; Nonferrous metal industries -- United States -- Defense measures; Open and closed shop -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Open and closed shop -- Steel industry -- United States; Open and closed shop -- Telecommunication -- United States; Pensions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Position classification -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Promotions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Law and legislation -- United States; Steel industry and trade -- Prices -- United States; Steel industry and trade -- Technological innovations -- United States; Steel industry and trade -- Military aspects -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Coal mining industry -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Musicians -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Performing artists -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Steel industry -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Stevedores -- United States; Technological innovations -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Union dues -- United States; Union dues -- United States -- Statistics; Union security -- Law and legislation -- United States; Union security -- United States; Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Stevedores -- Labor unions -- United States; Telecommunication -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Recognition; Airlines -- Employees -- Salaries, etc. -- United States; Wages -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Coal mining industry -- United States; Wages -- Fur trade -- United States; Wages -- Nonferrous metal industries -- United States; Wages -- Steel industry -- United States; Wages -- Stevedores -- United States; Wages -- Telecommunication -- United States; Wages -- Textile industry -- New England; Work assignments -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Work assignment -- Stevedores -- United States; Employee rules -- United States; Workers' compensation -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States -- Songs and music; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; Copper miners -- Labor unions; A. D. Julliard Company; AFL-CIO. Metal Trades Dept; Aircraft Workers Union; Amalgamated Workmen of America; American Can Company; American Communications Association; American Federation of Musicians; American Federation of Technical Engineers; American Radiator and Standard Sanitary Corporation; American Smelting and Refining Company; Anaconda Copper Mining Company; Appalachian Joint Conference; Associated Fur Coat and Trimming Manufacturers; Baker and Company, Inc.; Bendix Corporation; Bergen Point Iron Works; Bethlehem Steel Corporation; Brewers Board of Trade; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Celanese Chemical Company; Celanese Corporation of America; Chino Metal Trades Council of Grant County New Mexico; Eagle Electrical Manufacturing Company, Inc.; Electrical Transcription Manufacturers; Empire Zinc Company; Federation of Glass, Ceramic and Silica Sand Workers of America; Ford Colliers Company; Foremen's Association of America; Fur Floor Boys and Shipping Clerks Union; Furriers' Joint Council of New York; General Cable Corporation; General Electric Company; Gulf Oil Corporation; Helena Rubinstein, Inc.; Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America; Inland Steel Company; Inspirational Consolidated Copper Company; International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers; International Association of Machinists; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers, and Helpers; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; International Federation of Technical Engineers', Architects' and Draftsmen's Unions; International Harvester Company; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union; International Longshoremen's Association; International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers; International Union of Operating Engineers; International Union of United Brewery, Flour, Cereal, Soft Drink, and Distillery Workers of America; International Union of United Brewery, Flour, Cereal, Soft Drink, and Distillery Workers of America. Utica Local; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (A.F. of L.); Iron Ore Miners Federal Labor Union; Kennecott Copper Company; Kings County Light and Gas Employees Union (N.Y.); Kings County (N.Y.); National Association of Broadcasters; National Battery Company; National Bearing Company; National Union of United Aircraft Welders; Northwest Airlines; Pattern Makers' League of North America; Petroleum Trades Employees Union; Phelps Dodge Corporation; Postal Cable Company; R.H. Macy and Company; Republic Steel Corporation; Resurrection Mining Company; Sheffield Farms Associates; Sherwin-Williams Company; Southern Appalachian Joint Wage Conference; Southern Coal Producers Association; Steel Workers Organizing Committee; Swift and Company; Textile Workers Union of America; United Mine Workers of America. United Clerical, Technical and Supervisory Employees of the Mining Industry; United Department Store, Delivery and Interior Employees of Greater New York; United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America; United Gas, Coke, and Chemical Workers' International Union; United Mine Workers of America. District 20; United Office and Professional Workers of America; United Packinghouse Workers of America; United States. Dept. of Agriculture.; United States. Factfinding Board on the Pacific Longshore; United States. Factfinding Panel on the Bituminous Coal Industry; United States. Federal Communications Commission; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945). Region 2; United States. Nonferrous Metals Commission; United States Potash Company; United States Steel Corporation; United Steelworkers of America; Utah Copper Company; Utility Workers Organization Committee; Vanadium Corporation of America; W. L. Maxson Corporation; Waterfront Employers' Association; West Coast Airframe; Western Union Telegraph Company; Wright Aeronautical Corporation; Wright Aircraft Supervisors Association; Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company; Lapatin, Anne; Meyer, Arthur S., 1880-1955; Miller, Neville, 1894-1977; Paul, Lee G.
2293704
- West Coast Airframe Companies, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  January 8 1942
- West Coast Airframe Companies, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  January 9 1943
- Stabilization of the National Economy Basic Documents, Folder 1 of 2, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  February 1943
- Stabilization of the National Economy Basic Documents, Folder 2 of 2, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Steel Foundries, et. al. Case 14-47, et. al., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  October 11 1944
- Bethlehem Steel Company Case No. 111-2170-D, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Butler Brothers, et al Case 14-82 et al, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Central Indiana Case, Case No. 13-350-D, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ford Collieries Company, et al. Case No. 111-10258-D, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- General Electric, et al, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Little Steel Formula Vol. 1, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  April 4 1944
- Little Steel Formula Vol. 2, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  April 5 1944
- Little Steel Formula Vol. 3, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  April 6 1944
- Packard Motor Car Company, Case No. 111-5436-D, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Republic Steel Corporation, Case No. 5-D-486, File No. 111-4748-D, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Timken Roller Bearing Company, Case No. 14-363, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- United Steel Workers of America, Case No. 111-6230-D, 14-1 et al, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- United Steelworkers of America, Case No. 111-6230-D; 14-10;14-23;14-72;14-107, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- United Steelworkers of America, Case No. 111-6230-D 14-24; 14-322; 14-338; 14-229, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- National Labor Relations Board, Emily C. Brown, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Folder 1 of 2
- National Labor Relations Board, Emily C. Brown, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Folder 2 of 2
- Burnside Steel Foundry Company, Case No. 111-3249-D, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  June 15 1945
- Butler Brothers et al, Case No. 111-6230-D, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation, Case No. 111-7404-D, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, Case No. 111-6230-D, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  March 7 1945
- Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company, et al, Case No. 111-15751-D, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company, Case No. 8-L-1720, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Truscon Steel, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 1 and 2, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 3 and 4, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 5 and 6, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 7 and 8, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 9 and 10, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 11 and 12, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Northwest Airlines, Vol. 13 and 14, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Report to the President by the Emergency Board appointed September 18, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  October 7 1946
- Foreman's Association of America (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Summary of Significant Board Decisions, Complete Set 1-18, Vol. 1, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Summary of Significant Board Decisions, Complete Set No. 1-18, Vol. 1, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Summary of Significant Board Decisions, Complete Set No. 1-18, Vol. 2, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Summary of Significant Board Decisions, Complete Set No. 1-18, Vol. 2, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- War Labor Board Newsletter, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Folder 1 of 4
- War Labor Board Newsletter, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Folder 2 of 4
- War Labor Board Newsletter, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Folder 3 of 4
- War Labor Board Newsletter, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Folder 4 of 4